<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The exceptions of John Lilburne Gent. prisoner at the Barre, to a bill of indictment preferred against him, grounded upon a pretended act, intituled, An Act for the execution of a judgement given in Parliament against Lieutenant Collonel John Lilburn: which judgement is by the said Act supposed to be given the 15 day of January, 1651.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88184</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2108</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E705_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E708_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202791</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862968</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862968</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166623</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88184)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166623)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 109:E705[20] or 109:E708[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The exceptions of John Lilburne Gent. prisoner at the Barre, to a bill of indictment preferred against him, grounded upon a pretended act, intituled, An Act for the execution of a judgement given in Parliament against Lieutenant Collonel John Lilburn: which judgement is by the said Act supposed to be given the 15 day of January, 1651.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Moon, at the Seven-stars in Pauls Church-yard, near the great North-door,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Item at 109:E.705[20] signed at end: John Lilburne. Presented the 16 of July, 1653.</note>
                  <note>Item at 109:E.708[4] signed at end: Signed by his learned councel in the law, John Norbury, John Maynard ... and presented to and accepted by the lord mayor and honourable bench, July 16, 1653. John Lilburne.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copies: (E.705[20]) "July 16"; (E.708[4]) "July. 29.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166623:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
            <p>THE EXCEPTIONS OF <hi>John Lilburne</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>PRISONER at the BARRE, TO A Bill of Indictment Preferred againſt him, grounded upon a pretended Act, intituled, <hi>An Act for the Execution of a Judgement given in Parliament againſt Lieutenant Collonel</hi> John Lilburn: WHICH Judgement is by the ſaid Act ſuppoſed to be given the 15 day of <hi>January,</hi> 1651.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Moon,</hi> at the Seven-ſtars in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, near the great North-door, 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:166623:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166623:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
            <head>The Exceptions of <hi>John Lilburne</hi> Gent. Priſoner at the Bar to a Bill of Indictment preferred againſt him, grounded upon a pretended Act, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>An Act for the Execution of a Judgement given in Parliament againſt Lieutenant Collonel</hi> John Lilburn, which Judgement is by the ſaid Act ſuppoſed to be given the 15 day of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1651.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſaid <hi>John Lilburne</hi> Priſoner at the Bar ſaith, That the ſaid Indictment is inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in the Law; and he humbly offereth theſe Exceptions following againſt the ſame:</p>
            <div n="1" type="exception">
               <head>Except. <hi>1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The ſaid Indictment is grounded only upon an Act, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eituled, <hi>An Act for the execution of a judgement given in Parliament againſt Lieutenant Collonel</hi> John Lilburn; And it doth not appear, either by the Title of the ſaid Act re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited in the Indictment, or by any thing contained in the ſaid Act, that either the ſaid Act it ſelf, is an Act of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> or of the Parliament ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> or that the ſaid ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Judgement, for the execution whereof, the ſaid Act is ſuppoſed to provide, was given in the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> or in the Parliament ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> Nor yet when the ſaid Parliament did commence or end; or whether the ſame was held by proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or otherwiſe. And it is evident in Law, that no Law could at that time be made, but by the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England;</hi> for by the Law then in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the power of making Laws was only in thoſe perſons which were known and diſtinguiſhed by that Title of <hi>The
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166623:3"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->Parliament of the Commonwealth of England;</hi> and in that name only Addreſſes were made to them, both by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> and by all Forreign States and Princes, and all Addreſſes refuſed that wanted that Title. Now for ought that appears in the ſaid Act, whereupon the ſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment is grounded, it may be as well an Act of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Naples,</hi> as an Act of the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England;</hi> ſo that it doth not appear, that the ſaid Indictment is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Law of <hi>England;</hi> or that <hi>John Lilburne</hi> Priſoner at the Bar, is Indicted for any fact that is a Crime by any Law of <hi>England,</hi> and then the ſame is void in Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="exception">
               <head>Except. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The ſaid Indictment is grounded upon a pretended Act, intituled, <hi>An Act for the Execution of a Judgement given in Parliament againſt Lieutenant Colonel</hi> John Lilburne; and ſo relates only to ſome Judgement ſuppoſed to be given in Parliament againſt the ſaid Lieutenant Collonel <hi>John Lilburn;</hi> and if no ſuch Judgement were given, the Act were void, and the Judgement alſo. Now it doth not appear, that any Judgement for any Crime whatſoever, was given in Parliament againſt the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn.</hi> 1. Before any Judgement can be given in Law againſt any <hi>Engliſh</hi> man for any Crime, there muſt be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Indictment, Preſentment, or ſome Information or Accuſation againſt him; to that Court that judgeth him, for ſome crime ſuppoſed to be committed by him. 2. The party accuſed muſt either apear before that Court or be outlawed for not appearing. 3. If the party apears he muſt either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the crimes or miſdemeanors, wherof he is accuſed or elſ plead to the Indictment, preſentment or information, or accuſation againſt him, and come to tryal therupon. And as ſome of theſe ought in Law to precede a judgment againſt any Engliſh man, ſo alſo ſome of theſe afore-mentioned proceedings in order to a lawful jugment ought to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred upon ſuch Record, wherein any ſuch judgment is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, &amp; unleſs it doth appear upon the Record wherein any
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166623:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->judgment is entred againſt any Engliſhman for any crime, that ſom ſuch proceedings as aboveſaid have been made be fore the judgment paſſed againſt him, the judgment is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden for erroneous and void, and ought ſo to be reputed: now it doth not appear either by the ſaid pretended Act as it is recited in the Indictment, nor by any Record of the ſuppoſed judgment produced, nor any otherwiſe: that there was any Indictment, preſentment, or information to the Parliament of the Commonwealth of <hi>England</hi> againſt the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilborn,</hi> or if there were it doth not appear that he ever appeared to the ſame, nor that he was ever out-lawed for not appearing, neither doth any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi> to any ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment or information appear, not any tryal of him for the ſame; and therefore if any ſuch pretended judgment be entred, as the ſaid ſuppoſed Act, and the Indictment of <hi>John Lilburn</hi> priſoner at the Bar thereupon doth relate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, the ſame is erroneous and void in Law; and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence the ſaid Indictment is void.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="exception">
               <head>Except. <hi>3.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The ſaid Indictment is erroneous and inſufficient in Law for that it is onely grounded upon, and recites an Act, which Act is declared to be made for the execution of a judgment, paſſed in Parliament againſt Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>John Lilburne</hi> the Fifteenth day of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1651. when in truth there was no ſuch judgment either in matter or form paſſed in Parliament on the ſaid 15th day of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1651, as is enacted by the ſaid ſuppoſed Act to be executed againſt the ſaid Lieutenant Colonel <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> and as is alſo recited in the ſaid Indictment to be enacted by the ſaid act, to be put in execution againſt him. Firſt, there was no judgment, paſſed in Parliament upon the ſaid Fifteenth day of <hi>January</hi> 1651. That the ſaid Lieut. Col. <hi>John Liburn</hi> ſhould depart out of <hi>England</hi> within 20 dayes, after the ſaid 15th day of <hi>January</hi> 1651. as is mentioned in the ſaid Indictment. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly there was no judgment paſſed in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſaid Fifteenth day of <hi>January</hi> 1651. that the ſaid
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166623:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburn</hi> ſhould depart out of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> or the Iſlands, Territories, or Dominions thereof, within any limited time whatſoever, or under any penalty whatſoever, as is mentioned in the ſaid Indictment. 3: There never was any Judgment, paſſed in Parliament the ſaid 15 day of <hi>Jan.</hi> 1651. That the ſaid L. C. <hi>John Lilburne</hi> ſhould be executed as a Felon without benefit of Clergy, in caſe the ſaid Lieutenant Colonell <hi>John Lilburne</hi> ſhould be found, or be remaining in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> after the Expiration of Twenty dayes, or any other time whatſoever to be accompted from the ſaid Fifteenth day of January, 1651. and if no ſuch Judgment doth appear to have been paſſed againſt the ſaid Lieutenant Colonell <hi>John Lilburne</hi> as is aforeſaid, and as is recited by the ſaid Indictment to be Enacted to be put in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution againſt him, then the originall ground of the ſaid Indictment is nul and void: Which is a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuppoſed to be paſſed in Parliament againſt the ſaid Lieutenant Colonel <hi>John Lilburn</hi> in matter and form as aforeſaid, upon the 15 day of <hi>January</hi> 1651. which is enacted by the ſaid Act recited in the ſaid Indictment to be put in execution; whereas no ſuch Judgement ever paſſed; and therefore cannot be ſuppoſed or admitted by the Law to be enacted to be put in execution. And upon this ground the Priſoner at the Bar conceives the ſaid Judgement to be inſufficient in the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="exception">
               <head>Except. <hi>4.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> further excepts againſt the ſaid Indictment as inſufficient in the Law, in regard of the uncertainty of the ſame; the Law requiring all allegations againſt any man to be certain; for that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166623:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 49 -->the ſaid Indictment doth recite and ground it ſelf upon an Act made for the execution of a Iudgement paſſed in Parliament againſt Lieutenant Colonel <hi>John Lilburn.</hi> And then chargeth <hi>John Lilburn</hi> late of <hi>London</hi> Gentleman, to have been found in <hi>England;</hi> that is to ſay in <hi>London,</hi> contrary to the ſaid Act; but averreth not that the ſaid <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> now priſoner at the bar, Indicted by the name of <hi>John Lilburn</hi> late of <hi>London</hi> Gentleman is one and the ſame perſon with the ſaid Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>John Lilburn</hi> meant and intended by the ſaid Act, by reaſon whereof, and for that there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons known and diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> of <hi>London</hi> Gentleman; and for that the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> Priſoner at the Bar doth not acknowledge that he now is, or at the making of the ſaid Act, or paſſing the ſaid ſuppoſed Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was a Lieutenant Colonel, or that he could be notified and diſtinguiſhed by that Title. He the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> Priſoner at the Bar cannot joyn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny certain iſſue with the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>England</hi> upon the ſaid Indictment: for the ſaid Indictment not averring the ſaid <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> now Priſoner at the Bar to be the ſame perſon, and not other or divers from that <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> intended and meant in the ſaid Act, and diſtinguiſhed from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the ſame name, by the Title of a Lieutenant Colonel, if the Priſoner at the Bar ſhould plead the generall iſſue of not guilty, he ſhould confeſſe himſelf to be the ſame <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> intended by the ſaid Act; elſe he is not concerned to plead to the ſaid Indictment; and by conſequence, if the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at the Bar ſhould plead not guilty to the ſaid
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166623:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->Indictment, the only iſſue to be tryed in point of Fact between the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and the Priſoner, would be whether <hi>Iohn Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> priſoner at the bar was found in <hi>England</hi> upon the 15 day of <hi>Iune</hi> 1653. and by conſequence the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at the Bar, though he be not the perſon intended by the ſaid Act, might be enſnared and condemn'd as a Felon, only becauſe his name is <hi>Iohn Lirburn;</hi> and if any other <hi>Iohn Lilburn</hi> ſhould in like manner plead to the ſaid Indictment, he ſhould ſuffer becauſe he is called <hi>Iohn Lilburn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For all which errors and inſufficiencies in the Law in the ſaid Indictment, Act, and ſuppoſed judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſaid <hi>John Lilburn</hi> priſoner at the Bar, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly prayeth, that the ſaid Indictment may be qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and in caſe the honorable Court be not fully ſatisfied in the ſaid errors and inſufficiencies of the ſaid Indictment: He prayeth that Councel learned in the Laws may be aſſigned him, and a competent time given for him to adviſe with them, and for them to prepare their arguments upon all the ſaid matters of Law; and that the caſe being of very great difficulty, and much concernment to the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all the people of <hi>England,</hi> and being a caſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any preſident, and the ſhedding or ſparing of innocent blood, depending upon a reſolution thereof: He humbly prayeth, that the ſaid difficult points of Law, ariſing upon the caſe may be argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the reverend Judges of the Law, as hath been accuſtomed in ſuch caſes that their opinions may be had thereupon.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>John Lilburne.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Preſented</hi> 
                     <date>the 16 <hi>of July,</hi> 1653.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
